Guide to the Adelmann research materials collection, circa 1921-1963.
Adelmann research materials collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Adelmann research materials collection, circa 1921-1963.
4703
Howard B.(Howard Bernhardt), Adelmann 1898-,
Bound photocopies: ca. 312 v.Bound manuscripts: 1 v.Letters: 9 items.Microfilms: 17 linear ft. (366 reels).Unbound photocopies and photographs: 8 linear ft. (6 boxes).Glass slides: 35 slides.Wood blocks: 30 blocks.Metal plates: 10 plates.
Microfilm, Photographs, Printed Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists mainly of reproductions of manuscripts and some printed material by or about mainly 16th- and 17th-century Italian scientists, amassed and indexed by Howard B. Adelmann.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
American embryologist and historian of science; professor of histology and embryology at Cornell University, 1921-1963.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consists mainly of reproductions of manuscripts and some printed material by or about mainly 16th- and 17th-century Italian scientists, amassed and indexed by Howard B. Adelmann in the course of his research on the history of anatomy, embryology and histology. Materials focus especially on 17th-century Italian anatomists Marcello Malpighi and Hieronymus Fabricius ab Aquapendente, but also include Giorgio Baglivi, Francesco Redi, Lorenzo Bellini, Donato Rossetti, Henry Oldenburg, Giovanni Domenico Cassini, Johannes Bohn, Vincenzo Busacchi, Giovanni Domenico Guglielmini, Albrecht von Haller, Luigi Ferdinando Marsili, Giambattista Morgagni, Antonio Francesco Ghiselli, Giovanni Alfonso Borelli, and others.
Includes also original autograph letters by Marcello Malpighi (6 items) and Gaetano Atti (3 items); manuscript Tractatus in libros de generatione (17th century), on reproduction, sensation, and the theory of knowledge; typescript bibliography of the works of Fabricius; typescript with pencilled notes on manuscripts by Malpighi; and glass slides including portraits of Malpighi. Libraries where unbound photocopies were made are not identified; wood blocks and their origin are also unidentified.
Additional bound photocopies include works by and about Malpighi, and works by Ulisse Aldrovandi, Thomas Bartholin, Lorenzo Bellini, Georges Cuvier, Luigi Ferdinando Marsili, Giambattista Morgagni, Lorenz Oken, Francesco Redi, and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Adelmann, Howard B.1898- ,; Adelmann, Howard B.(Howard Bernhardt), 1898-; Baglivi, Giorgio,; Bellini, Lorenzo, 1643-1704.; Bohn, Johannes, 1640-1718.; Borelli, Giovanni Alfonso, 1608-1679.; Busacchi, Vincenzo.; Cassini, Giovanni Domenico, 1625-1712.; Fabricius, ca. 1533-1619.; Ghiselli, Antonio Francesco.; Guglielmini, Giovanni Domenico.; Haller, Albrecht von, 1708-1777.; Malpighi, Marcello, 1628-1694.; Marsili, Luigi Ferdinando, 1658-1730.; Morgagni, Giambattista, 1682-1771.; Oldenburg, Henry, 1615?-1677.; Redi, Francesco, 1626-1698.; Rossetti, Donato.
Subjects:
Anatomy--History--Sources.; Embryology--History--Sources.; Histology--History--Sources.; Anatomists--Italy.; Medical scientists--Italy.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
112 v. of bound photocopies cataloged separately.
CONTAINER LIST
- Achillini - Anatomicae Annot., 1520 (Box 26)
- Aldrovandus - Orinthologiae Lib. XIV (Box 30)
- Ammon - Entwickslungsgeschichte des Menchlichen Auges., 1832 (Box 26)
- Ammon - Bildung des Vogelauges, 1833 (Box 26)
- Ammon - Entwickslungsgeschichte des Auges., 1844 (Box 26)
- Anon - G.A. Borelli (Box 25)
- Arantius - De Humano Foetu, 1579 (Box 27)
- Arenaprimo - Lettori dello Studio Messinese, 1900 (Box 27)
- Arenaprimo - Borelli a Malpighi, 1906 (Box 25)
- Arnold - Auges des Menschen, 1832 (Box 26)
- Arnold - Membrana Capsulo-Pupillaris, 1833 (Box 26)
- Atti - Malpighi, 1835 (Box 27)
- Atti - Lettera di L. Bellini, 1847 (Box 25)
- Atti - Vtia di Malpighi, 1839 (Box 25)
- Averroes - Paraphrasis, 1890 (Box 27)
- Barbensi - Malpigi, 1954 (Box 27)
- Barner - Exercitium Chimiae, 1670 (Box 27)
- Battistella - Processi D'Eresia, 1901 (Box 27)
- Bellini - De Struct. Renum, 1662 (Box 27)
- Bellini (Molinari-Atti) - Lettere, 1844 (Box 25)
- Belon - L'Histoire des Poissons, 1551 (Box 26)
- Benedictus - Anatomice (Box 27)
- Berres - Foramen Centrale Retinae Humanae, 1833 (Box 27)
- Berthold - Testis, 1845 (Box 27)
- Bilancioni - Malpighi- Senso del Gusto, 1928 (Box 27)
- Blasius - Formatio Intestinorum, 1823 (Box 27)
- Bohn - De Generationis Doctrina, 1854 (Box 27)
- Bonaretti - Poetico Estratto di Gloria, 1674 (Box 25)
- Bonomi - Osservazioni, 1687 (Box 25)
- Castro - A Castro Mulierum Medicina (Box 30)
- Camper - De Analogia Inter Animalia et Stirpes, 1764 (Box 27)
- Capparoni - Ritratto di Malpighi, 1928 (Box 27)
- Carpi - Commentaria (Box 27)
- Castiglioni - Bologna, 1945 (Box 27)
- Cazin - Estomac des Oiseaux, 1887 (Box 27)
- Coiter - De Ouorum Exordio, 1573 (Box 30)
- Collins - Anatomy, 1685 (Box 27)
- Cooper - Testis, 1830 (Box 30)
- Cooper - Testis, 1841 (Box 30)
- Cowper - Descrip. Gland., 1702 (Box 27)
- Daglio - Malpighi- Sistema Nervoso, 1955 (Box 27)
- Dall'ossa - Malpighi-Albertini, 1956 (Box 27)
- Dall'ossa - Pesci-Consulti-Albertinni, 1956 (Box 27)
- Daniels - Hist D'un Livre, 1886 (Box 27)
- De Back - De Corde (Box 26)
- Del Gaizo - Motus Anim Borelli, 1914 (Box 27)
- Del Gaizo - Borelli, 1980 (Box 30)
- Del Gaizo - Lettera di Malpighi, 1919 (Box 25)
- DeMaria - Elogio Storico di Luigi Rolando, 1846 (Box 28)
- Diemerbroeck - Anatome, 1679 (Box 28)
- Diemerbroeck - Anatome, 1683 (Box 28)
- Diemerbroeck - Anatome, 1685 (Box 28)
- Droysen - Renibus et Capsulis Renalibus, 1752 (Box 28)
- Dursy - Urniere, 1865 (Box 28)
- Dursy - Messungen, 1867 (Box 28)
- Dutrochet - Enveloppes du Foetus, 1817 (Box 28)
- Dutrochet - L'Oeuf des Oiseaux, 1819 (Box 28)
- Enders - Epoophoron, 1902 (Box 28)
- Fabretti - Elogio di Malpighi, 1721 (Box 25)
- Fabroni - Vita Malpighi, 1769 (Box 25)
- Fabroni - Vita Malpighi, 1779 (Box 25)
- Fernel - De Medicina, 1554 (Box 30)
- Ferraresi - Canali di Gartner, 1897 (Box 28)
- Ferraresi - Canali di Gartner, 1897 (Box 28)
- Ferrari - Zelotypia, 1690 (Box 25)
- Forni - Persiceto, 1921 (Box 28)
- Fracassati - Oratio in Funere Massarii, 1655 (Box 25)
- Fracassati et al - Oratio in Funere Mariani Habita, 1662 (Box 25)
- Franzel - Sclerotica Choroidea, 1830 (Box 28)
- Frati - Medaglie di Malpighi, 1856 (Box 25)
- Fulchignoni - Malpighi Sui Sensi del Gusto E. del Tatto, 1938 (Box 25)
- Geoffroy - An Homimis Primordia. Vermis?, 1704 (Box 28)
- Giordani - Villa Malpighi- Salina (Frati-107), 1841 (Box 25)
- Giordani - Villa Malpighi- Salina (Frati-108), 1841 (Box 25)
- Goidanich - Primi Documenti, 1941 (Box 28)
- Gottsche - Uber den Bau der Retina, 1836 (Box 28)
- Gottsche - Ueber das Pigment des Auges, 1836 (Box 28)
- Guglielmini - Oratio (Frati 73), 1734 (Box 25)
- Guthrie - Bladder, 1834 (Box 28)
- Hahn - Theorien der Epigenese U. Eveolution, 1823 (Box 28)
- Hanuschke - De Genitalium Evolutione, 1837 (Box 28)
- Henle - De Membrana Pupillari, 1832 (Box 28)
- Hennig - Der Katarrh, 1862 (Box 28)
- Hoffmann - Comm. In de Usu, 1625 (Box 28)
- Hofmann - Institutiones, 1645 (Box 28)
- Home - Prevost, 1823 (Box 28)
- Huschke - Streitpuncte, 1833 (Box 28)
- Huschke - Uber Einige Streitpuncte, 1835 (Box 28)
- Huschke - Hoden, 1844 (Box 28)
- Jenritza - De Hominis Generatione, 1841 (Box 28)
- Kiesselbach - Evolutionis Nervi Sympathici, 1835 (Box 28)
- Kob - De Mutatione Sexus, 1823 (Box 28)
- Kupffer - Enstetlung, 1864 (Box 28)
- Langly - Schrader- Obervationes, 1674 (Box 28)
- L'Archiginnasio - I. Indice Bologna, 1906-1935 (Box 28)
- L'Archiginnasio - II. Indice Bologna, 1936-1965 (Box 28)
- Laurenzi - Tributo Lugubre, 1693 (Box 25)
- Lealis - De Partibus, 1707 (Box 29)
- Lesky - Zeugungslehre, 1950 (Box 29)
- Libavius - De Ovi Gallinarum, 1610 (Box 29)
- Liberkuhn - Auges des Wirbelthier-Embryo, 1871 (Box 29)
- Lilienfeld - Zur Morphologie U. Entwick, Der Geschlectsorgane, 1856 (Box 29)
- Lipari - Galenistarum See Malpighi- Conclusiones- Apologia (Box 25)
- Lipari - Galenistarum Triumphus, 1665 (Box 29)
- Lipari - Malpighi-Conclusiones See Galenistarum Triumphus (Box 29)
- Lisfranc - Urethra, 1824 (Box 25)
- Lovarini - Discorsi Astrologici, 1912 (Box 25)
- Malpighi - De Pulmonibus, 1930 (Box 25)
- Malpighi - Conclusiones- Apologia (Box 25)
- Malpighi - Memorie di Me, 1902 (Box 25)
- Malpighi - Ritrovamenta dei Manoscritti di Malpighi (Frati, 94-98) (Box 26)
- Mandosio - Theatron, 1784 (Box 29)
- Marchetti - Anatomia, 1690 (Box 29)
- Marsili - Observaxioni Intorno al Bosforo, 1681 (Box 29)
- Mauros - Uber Die Zeugung in all Gemeinen, 1827 (Box 29)
- Mayoor - De Mascula Sobole Procreanda, 1723 (Box 29)
- Meckel - Tr. Cuview e, 1809 (Box 29)
- Medici - Vita e Scritti Degli Anatomici Bologna, 1853 (Box 29)
- Messina - CCCL. Anniversario, 1900 (Box 29)
- Meyer und Wolf - Vogelkunde, 1810 (Box 29)
- Meyerstein - Ueber die Eileiter, 1865 (Box 29)
- Moleschott - Menschen und der Theire, 1870 (Box 29)
- Monalbani - Antineotiologia, 16- (Box 29)
- Morawa - Generatione Notatu, 1820 (Box 29)
- Morel - De Generatione, 1787 (Box 29)
- Morgagni - Adversaria, 1719 (Box 30)
- Muller - Ueber das Coloboma Iridis, 1830 (Box 29)
- Munster - Malpighi E Baglivi, 1949 (Box 25)
- Neumann - De Exclusione Ovulorum, 1717 (Box 29)
- Neviani - Lettera di Marsili a Malpighi (Box 25)
- Noortwyk - De Natura Humana, 1735 (Box 29)
- Oellacher -, 1869 (Box 29)
- Oken - Lehrb. d. Naturg. -III, 1816 (Box 29)
- Origonis - Erzeugung u. Ihren Theorien, 1843 (Box 29)
- Orlando-Salinas - Malpigi, 1928 (Box 29)
- Orlando-Salinas - Malpighi, 1928 (Box 29)
- Pander - Metamorphoses, 1817 (Box 30)
- Pander - Ovum Incubatum, 1817 (Box 30)
- Parenti - Lettera Malpighi a Ramazzini, 1839 (Box 25)
- Parosanus - De Foetu, 1621 (Box 30)
- Paulus Minus - Medicus Igne, 1678 (Box 26)
- Phil Vet. Et Nov. - Bergundia, 1681 (Box 30)
- Photiades - Nonulla de Generatione, 1838 (Box 30)
- Pinto - Taddeo da Fiorenza, 1888 (Box 30)
- Plagge - Ovi Mammalium See Cazin - Estomac des Oiseaux (Box 27)
- Puteus - Apologia, 1562 (Box 30)
- Rambelli - Due Lettere di Malpighi, 1834 (Box 26)
- Rathke - Auges Beim Schleimfisch, 1833 (Box 30)
- Re - Discorso (Frati 85), 1810 (Box 26)
- Redi - Tre Lettere, 1903 (Box 30)
- Reich - De Membrana Pupillari, 1833 (Box 30)
- Richter - Letters Aromatari, 1662 (Box 26)
- Robertson - Grew, 1906 (Box 30)
- Roederer - De Foetu Perfecto, 1750 (Box 30)
- Roesslein - De Differentiis Inter Foetum et Adultum, 1783 (Box 30)
- Rolando - Organogenesie, 1823 (Box 30)
- Rolando - Organogenesia, 1822-28 (Box 26)
- Rolando-Coeur - Canal Alimentaire, 1823 (Box 30)
- Roose - De Superfoetatione Nonnulla, 1801 (Box 30)
- Rusconi - Due Lettere di Redi, 1839 (Box 26)
- Samter - De Evolutione Ovi Avium, 1853 (Box 30)
- Sbaraglia - De Recent. Med. Stud.- Gott, 1687 (Box 26)
- Sbaraglia - Dissertationes Quibus Moderna Medicorum Studia Ventilantur, 1693 (Box 26)
- Scaliger - (on) Theophrastus, 1566 (Box 30)
- Seerich - De Generatione, 1834 (Box 30)
- Senk-Eisen - De Generatione, 1802 (Box 30)
- Simili - Cardano, 1940 (Box 31)
- Sorbelli - Almanacchi Bolognesi, 1931 (Box 26)
- Sprye - De Fluxu Menstruo, 1685 (Box 26)
- Stokes - Malpighi and his Writings, 1910 (Box 30)
- Suringar - De Nisu Formativo, 1824 (Box 31)
- T. Bartholin - Anatomia, 1651 (Box 30)
- T. Bartholin - Anatomia, 1651 (Box 27)
- Thiersch - Bildungsfeheler, 1852 (Box 31)
- Tiedemann - Der Vogel, 1810 (Box 31)
- Tiedemann - Zoologie, 1814 (Box 31)
- Trew - De Differentiis, 1736 (Box 31)
- Valenti - Organi Rudimentali, 1885 (Box 31)
- Valsalva - Opera, 1740 (Box 31)
- Varolius - Anatomia, 1591 (Box 31)
- Vecchietti (bib. Picena) - Divini Eustach Cecco, 1884 (Box 26)
- Velpeau - Anat. Chir/, 1833 (Box 30)
- Ventimiglia - Orazione, 1839 (Box 31)
- Volkmann - Coluber, 1834 (Box 31)
- Wachendorff - Commercii Litteraraii- Pupillary Membrane, 1740 (Box 31)
- Wachendorff -, 1740 (Box 31)
- Waldeyer -, 1869 (Box 31)
- Weber - Uteri et Ovariorum Puellae, 1830 (Box 31)
- Weber - Uterus Puellae, 1830 (Box 31)
- Weber - Geschlects-Organe, 1846 (Box 31)
- Weiss - Malpighi sue Opere, 1884 (Box 26)
- Wenzel - Structura Cerebri, 1812 (Box 30)
- Wittich -, 1853 (Box 31)
- Wrisberg - Commentationes, 1800 (Box 31)
- Zeno - Cont. Sbaraglia col Malpighi, 1710 (Box 31)
- Zerbi - Anatomia, 1502 (Box 31)
- Zerbi - Anatomia, 1502 (Box 31)
- Zuno - Malpighiana, 1929 (Box 31)